Contact

518-321-2056 (Mobile) balalouann@gmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/louann-balamsn-rn-10a26253 (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

Hospitals

Healthcare Management

Healthcare

Languages

spanish (Elementary)

English

Certifications

Progressive Care Certified Nurse

Nurse Manager Boot Camp

NIHSS Certification

FEMA Distaster Preparedness Certificate

Honors-Awards

YWCA Reach Award Winner

Publications

Low Bed Implementation to reduce injuries from Falls on the Neuroscience Unit Health Care Association of New York State

How Digital Health Solutions Can Help Hospitals Eliminate Opportunities for Error

The Business Case for Complementary Therapy: A Feasibility Study

Stroke and Risk for Falls: Preventing Secondary Injury

Capacity for Evidence-based Practice at Ellis Medicine

LouAnn Bala' MSN, RN

VP/CNO/Product Strategy

Argyle, New York

Summary

An experienced transformational nursing leader and trusted consultant with over two decades of progressive leadership and operational experience in a variety of settings. Established leader with an intense focus on operations, change management, strategic planning, team building, exceeding customer expectations, and driving financially sound, high quality results. Process expert on developing revenue enhancing service line strategies, right sizing services and executing high impact, highly reliable organizational strategies.

Experience

GetWellNetwork
VP/CNO/ Product Strategy, Acute Care Solutions
March 2015 - Present (5 years 5 months)
Argyle, New York

Ellis Medicine

9 years 11 months

Associate Chief Nursing Officer April 2014 - March 2015 (1 year)

Schenectady, New York

Oversight of 12 direct reports with budgetary responsibility for 381 FTE's, \$35.8 million dollar operating budget. 12 units including multi-campus Emergency Services, Critical Care and Cardiothoracic Services, Progressive Care, Inpatient and Crisis Mental Health Services, Outpatient Infusion, Wound Care and Interventional Services.

Selected Accomplishments:

- •Exceeded National average for Patient Satisfaction, Emergent Care
- •Developed PCU for Cardiothoracic Services, reduced LOS by 0.5 days; Reduced agency costs in the ICU by \$400,000 per month; reduced vacancy

rate from 30% to less than 3% in 6 months

- •Completed \$61. million dollar renovation and expansion project for Emergency Services
- •Project Lead for ED Consolidation in Schenectady post-merger; reduced inappropriate ED utilization by approximately 10,000 patients (annualized)
- •Co-Led Redesign of Capacity Optimization hospital wide; projected \$2.5 million dollar loss turned into a \$6.6 million dollar surplus
- •Redesigned staffing model for Emergency Services; Increased productivity from 86% to 100%

Director Emergency Services, Multi-Campus April 2013 - March 2015 (2 years)

Schenectady, New York

Reported directly to the Vice President of Patient Care Services/CNO. Responsible for the oversight of 7 direct reports, 162 FTEs with an overall operating budget of over \$11.2 million, 4 units on three campuses including Nott Street Emergency Department and Crisis Center (65,000 visits combined), Emergent Care Center of Clifton Park (36,000 visits), McClellan Campus Free Standing Emergency Department (36,000 visits).

Selected Accomplishments:

- Achieved 107% YTD Productivity Target Combined
- •Implemented Electronic Medical Record and Medication System
- •Redesigned Triage Process; improved LWBS from 7% to 5%; reduced door to room by 50%
- •Obtained grant funding to support SANE certification; certified 15 nurses over 2 years
- Improved EKG times from 20 minutes to less than 10 minutes consistently;
 Met STEMI goals of less than 90 minutes door to balloon time YTD 2014
 Jointly Implemented TPA Neuro-Nurse Program; door to needle times consistently below 60 minutes

Director Critical Care/Cardiothoracics October 2012 - April 2013 (7 months)

Schenectady, New York

Reported to the Vice President Patient Care Services/CNO. 24/7 accountability for 36 bed Intensive Care Unit providing oversight for 120 FTE's, with an \$8.8 million operating budget. Interim Secondary Position.

Selected Accomplishments:

- •Eliminated agency costs estimated savings approximately \$430,000 per month
- Achieved monthly productivity targets of 96-110% consistently
- •Reduced CLABSI from 20% infection rate to 0%

•Improved Charge Capture for low volume high cost supplies; increased revenue by 143,000 in 4 months

Director, Magnet Program
March 2009 - April 2013 (4 years 2 months)
Schenectady, New York

Reported to the Vice President Patient Care Services/CNO. Organization on the Journey to Magnet. Developing organizational structure, establishing research institute, conducting assessments and bridging gaps and special projects as assigned. In charge of a \$300,000 professional nursing education budget. Co-Led Nurse/Physician Research Initiatives. Active Member of the IRB.

Selected Accomplishments:

- •Increased Nursing Certifications by 150%; Increased Clinical Ladder Participation by 300%
- •Increased participation in BSN programs by 50% over 2 years; Acquired 10 articulation agreements over a one year period of time
- •Met meaningful use guidelines through implementation of EHR; received \$3.6 million in 2011, and \$2.9 million in 2012
- •Received MassExcellence Baldrige Quality Awards, Silver (2011), Gold (2012); Authored Customer Focus Content and Measurements Sections

Nurse Manager Neurosciences/Med Tele/ICU May 2005 - March 2009 (3 years 11 months) Schenectady, New York

Reported to the Director of Nursing Services. 24/7 unit responsibility, 65 direct reports and a \$2.7 million dollar operating budget.

Selected Accomplishments:

- •Achieved NYSDOH Gold and Gold Plus Awards (2007,2008,2009)
- Designed Neuroscience Bundle, reduced falls by 90%; Achieved one full year of zero CLABSI, and VAP
- •Increased patient satisfaction scores from the 50th to the 99th percentile in one year
- •Project Lead, integration of EMU, increased revenue by approximately \$96,000 annually
- •Maintained turnover less than 4% for 3 years
- •Led Lean Waste Reduction Initiative; reduced costs by 250,000 in 6 months

Interim Director Neurosciences
March 2008 - December 2008 (10 months)
Schenectady, New York

Reported to VP of Clinical Services. Oversight of inpatient and outpatient neuro-diagnostic laboratory consisting of 8 Technical FTE's, 5 Neurologists and 4 Neurosurgeons. Interim Secondary Position.

•Project Lead, implementing IOM Program for Neurosurgical High Risk Procedures; increased revenue by approximately \$100 per case

•Improved turnaround time for outpatient dictated reports from 72 hours to 24 hours

Winter Haven Hospital
Per Diem Staff RN Medical Surgical Telemetry
March 2003 - March 2005 (2 years 1 month)

Winter Haven, Florida

Florida Hospital

Assistant Nurse Manager Post Cardiac Catheterization Unit/Staff Nurse Cardiothoracic Step Down Unit 2004 - 2005 (1 year)

Reported to the Nurse Manager of Cardiac Intervention, accountability for a 65 bed unit with approximately 90 FTE's. Florida Hospital is a Seventh Day Adventist not for profit, 1100-bed acute-care Hospital, serving the Greater Orlando Region. The hospital is a major tertiary referral hospital for Central Florida and much of the Southeast, the Caribbean and Latin America. It is part of the largest not-for-profit protestant health care system in the United States. Known for cardiac care and cardiothoracic services with an average of 140 heart catheterizations and over 20 open heart procedures per day. Selected Accomplishments:

- •Achieved Patient Satisfaction Scores in the 99th percentile YTD 2004
- •Led unit governance council; improved nurse communication scores to the 99th percentile
- •Achieved 100% hand hygiene compliance
- •Received Joint Commission Re-accreditation and recognition for cultural awareness program

Florida Hospital Orlando

Progressive Care Post Cardiothoracic Unit Relief Charge RN 2003 - 2004 (1 year)

Reported to the Nurse Manager of Progressive Care. 65 bed post open coronary bypass unit.

Selected Accomplishments:

•Participated in quality improvement programs; 100% compliance discharging patients on ace inhibitors and cholesterol lowering medications YTD 2004

•Achieved patient satisfaction scores in the 99th percentile over two years

Cross Country TravCorps
Travel Nurse Cardiothoracics
2001 - 2003 (2 years)
Boca Raton, Florida

Portsmouth Regional Hospital Charge Nurse/Staff Nurse 1999 - 2001 (2 years)

Portsmouth, New Hampshire

Reported to the Nurse Manager of Progressive Care. Portsmouth Regional Hospital is a 209-bed community hospital serving the Seacoast Area. Known for Heart and Vascular Care

- •Team Member, Improved Nurse Handoffs; decreased report off time by 15 minutes without reducing quality outcomes
- •Supervised and oriented new staff; 100% retention after 1 year

Lakeview NeuroRehabilitation Medication Stat Nurse 1999 - 2001 (2 years) Effingham, New Hampshire

Reported to the Director for Clinical Services. Responsible for patient safety and quality of care for pediatric, adolescent and adult traumatic brain injury survivors in a multi-dorm, long term care environment. Lakeview Neuro-rehab is a leader in Neuro-behavioral modification and neuro-rehabilitation post ICU and Acute Injuries.

Saratoga Hospital Staff Nurse Cardiology 1998 - 1999 (1 year) Saratoga Springs, New York

Reported to the Nurse Manager of Telemetry on a 25 bed unit. Saratoga hospital is a 243 bed, Magnet, not for profit community hospital serving Saratoga County.

Four Winds Health Charge Nurse 1996 - 1998 (2 years) Saratoga, New York

Shift accountability for patient safety and quality of care outcomes for up to 20 children. Reported to the Director Clinical Services. Multi-dorm long term care Psychiatric Facility providing inpatient and outpatient mental health treatment services for children, adolescents and adults. Leading specialized providers of inpatient psychiatric treatment in the northeast.

Private Duty Nurse Independent Contractor September 1996 - November 1996 (3 months)

Camp Little Notch
Camp Nurse
May 1996 - September 1996 (5 months)

Reported to the Camp Director and offsite Supervising Physician. Camp Little Notch is a privately owned Girl Scout Camp. Accountability for medication administration, triage, wellness education and child abuse screening for over 50 campers and families. Served as the onsite clinical resource.

Selected Accomplishment:

Successfully completed NYS Department of Health Inspection

Education

University of Phoenix

Bachelor's Degree, Registered Nursing/Registered Nurse · (2006 - 2008)

University of Phoenix

Master's degree, Nursing (2008 - 2009)

Adirondack Community College

Associate's degree Applied Science, Nursing (1994 - 1996)